字幕：刘洋， 北京石油化工学院，2012年11月
What we for the sake of convinience called 'a chip'?
为了省事，我们把什么称作"芯片"?
It's offically called 'an IC'.
它的官方名称是“IC”，
the abbrevation for 'integrated circuit'.
“集成电路”的简称。
A chip is like a city.
一块芯片就像一座城市。
A city without no people but bursting with activity.
这城市里没有人，但是充斥着活动。
A chip is packed with industrial buildings, control centers in the form of components,such as transistors, and resistants.
一块芯片内被晶体管、电阻等元件组成的“工业建筑”、控制中心挤满。
which together form one huge network.
这些“建筑”“中心”一起形成了一个巨大的网络。
The chip's infastructure carries a burst amounts of fars traffic long roads intercommunication networks.
芯片的内部结构包含了一个由海量线路组成的内部通信网络。
The buildings locked in a chip are not only becoming smaller, but our designers are also making the chips cleverer all the time.
封在芯片中的“建筑”不仅一直在变小，而且我们的设计师正在使芯片变得越来越聪明。
So this creates new possibilities continuously.
于是，这持续不断地带来新的可能性；
This makes the equipment controlled by the chips better：safer, easy to operate, more energy efficient, and friendly at the environment.
让芯片所控制的设备性能越来越好：更安全、易操作、更节能、而且环境友好。
Let's drive in certainly boosts throught the ingenious process by means which products such as chips are produced at Pheonix 984.
让我们来看看芯片制造的神奇工艺吧。
We explain an expect such as the most important steps in the production of ICs.
我们预期将解释一些IC生产过程中最重要的工序步骤。
And to make this easier to understand. We'll begin with the series of animations.
为了更宜于理解，我们从一系列动画开始。
A chip is a extremely small silicon plate ranging from a couple to several dozens square millimetres in size.
芯片是是一片非常小的硅片，尺寸从几到几十平方毫米之间。
This tiny silicon plate is then filled up with a great number, sometimes millions of microelements, such as transistors, diodes, or resistants.
这小硅片充满了大量的微元件，如晶体管、二极管、或电阻。
which together form integrated circuit, the 'IC'.
这些微元件一起组成了集成电路，IC。
We make a large number of chips on a round.
我们在同一块硅圆片上制备大量的芯片。
on a round silicon disk, called 'a wafer or slice'.
而这块硅圆片称为硅晶圆或硅晶片。
First of all, we create a new layer of silicone on the slice, one hundred several nanaometers thick.
首先，我们在硅晶圆上沉积一层100多纳米厚的硅。
We then oxidize the silicon layer in a oven.
然后，我们将这层硅在炉子中氧化。
So an even thinner isolating layer is created on the top of it.
于是一层均匀的绝缘薄膜在硅晶圆上形成。
We then apply a coat of light sensitive Laica.
然后，我们涂覆一层光敏的涂层。
We expose the Laica through a kind of photographic negative.
将这光敏涂层在光负胶片下曝光。
Serve the Laica dissolved in certain places.
然后，将特定区域的光敏涂料溶去。
Then in the places where there is no more Laica. We shoot atoms with great accuracy through the oxide layer into the silicon.
于是，我们将原子高精度地射向这些没有光敏涂料的区域，原子穿透了氧化层进入硅晶格中。
The layer of Laica is no longer required. And is therefor removed from the slice.
此时，不再需要表面的光敏涂层，因此，光敏涂层被从硅晶圆上除去。
We then assure the atoms penetrate a little deeper into the silicon by a few thousandths of  millimetre.
我们确保这些原子渗入硅晶中千分之几毫米的深度。
A new silicon layer is applied over the oxide layer.
在氧化层上又构建一层新的硅。
And once again a new layer of Laica is applied, exposed, and developed.
进而重复操作，新的光敏涂层被涂上、曝光、冲洗。
The silicon, which is uncovered by the process, is then etched away.
在这个过程中，未被覆盖的硅晶之后被刻蚀掉。
接着，进行下一系列的操作：光敏涂层、曝光、原子渗入硅晶、新的氧化层。
Another series of fitments involving Lacicaring, exposure, on bottoments with the atoms
which penetrate the silicon, new oxide layer etc. is performed
until the whole patternism complete in all its layers. 直至在所有层都构筑好图形。
Some three hundred to four hundred process steps are required
这个过程需要执行三百至四百步操作，
along fifteen to twenty  different masks with microscopically small patterns.
使用15至20片有微图形的掩膜(负胶片)。
最后一个步骤是将硅片中大量的肉眼不可见的微小元件连接起来。
The final step in the process is the connection of a various honestly invisible tiny  elements in the silicon.
这就是我们如何制造一个电子回路，IC，或者芯片。
This is how we make an electonic circuit, an IC or a chip.
Naturally, we have a good relationship with our suppliers.
自然，我们和供货商有着良好的关系。
As they too play a part in determining the quality of our products.
因为他们也对我们产品的品质有影响。
Silicon is made from ordinary quartz sand.
硅是由普通石英砂制备而来
然后，硅棒在很高温度下被制造或者提拉出来的。
And rods of silicon are then created or drawn at extremely high temperatures.
Thin slices are then sawn on the roll with great accuracy.
之后，这根硅棒被十分精确切割成硅片。
The ICs will be produced on these slices of silicon,
IC将从这些硅片来制造。
为了达到这个目标，这些硅片将经历300至400步工艺。
for which purpose, the slices will undergo three hundred to four hundred processes.
在这个特殊的炉子中，硅晶圆将被覆盖上一层薄而纯的硅。
In this special oven, the slices are covered by a new thin layer of very pure silicon,
这层硅将被用于构建晶体管和其它一些元件。
into  which transistors and other components can be built.
覆盖了新硅层的硅晶圆被置于其它盒子中。
The slices with the new layer of silicon are placed in other boxes,
在这些盒子中这些硅将被氧化。
where the silicon is  allowed to oxidize.
如果有对需要的话，这些绝缘的氧化层将在下一步骤中被除去。
This isolating oxide layer can be removed in next stage when necessary.
This is known as 'the yellow room'.
这是有名的“黄色房间”。
高智能全自动的机械被用来给硅片的氧化层涂上光敏层，并将光敏层曝光。
Yet, extremely intelligent fully automative machines are used to apply the light sensitive  layer of Laica to the oxide on the slices, and to expose the slices.
之所以在这房间里使用黄光，是因为光敏层对黄光不敏感。
Yelow light is used in this room, as the Laica is not sensitive to this.
掩膜上的图形是负胶片状的，当然是由我们的技术支持工程师所设计的。
The patterns on the masks are kind of negative, are of course designed by our own  development engineers.
The templates themselves are made by other specialists.
而这些模板是由其他专家制造的。
当然，我们也与原料供应商和设备生产商有着良好的合作。
It goes without saying that we also coorperate very plesy with the supplies and equipment  manufacturings.
在这个离子注入机里，特定的原子被迅速的注入到硅层的一些区域，以赋予它们正的或负的导电性能。
In this so-called implanters, specific atoms can be shortenly implanted in areas of the  silicon to give them positive or negative conductivity.
This is done incredibly accurately.
这个操作的精度难以置信。
例如，将一个原子注入在十万个硅原子之中。
For example, one atom in a hundred thousands silicon atoms.
One of the next steps in process is ething.
后续工序中有一步骤称为刻蚀：
Removing materials locally from the slices with great accuracy.
即从硅晶片的局部精确地移除一些材料。
这个部分使用自动控制过程，涉及到酸和腐蚀。
This department uses an automatic controlled process involving acids and coustics.
另一种使用的技术是在刻蚀气氛下进行的“干法刻蚀”。
Another technique used is 'dry ething' with a ething gas.
这张图片给出了涉及到“干法刻蚀”的一些技术。
This picture gives an impression of technologies involved in this 'dry etching'.
我们在此所见的一切工艺步骤以及一些更多的工序被不断的重复直至产品完全组装完毕。
All the process steps we've seen and many many more are repeated until the products has been  fully assembled.
这是通过一台特殊的电子显微镜所看到的一些最小的部分。
This is what the smallest parts look like through a special electronic microscope.
有时芯片设计师们使用一种技术，将芯片锯开，因此能看到芯片的内部结构。
Sometimes the chip designers use a technique in which the chip is sawn through, so you can  even look inside.
在这个制程中的最后一步是把硅片中各种元件连接起来。
The last stpe in the process involves making connections between the verious elements in the  silicon.
它们是如此之小以至于要使用微尺度的真空沉积来制备它们。
These are so tiny that a miniscu vaccum deposited layer of aluminium is required to make them.
完成这个过程要经历3周，并由可见的检测来确定过程的结束。
Each chip is checked for a number of essential functions.
每块芯片要通过许多关键检测。
检测后，那些达不到技术标准的芯片用墨点标记出来，并不再使用这些芯片。
After detesting, chips which do not comply with the specification are marked with a ink dot, so will no longer be used.
Once they've been tested, the chips are ready for assembling.
一旦芯片通过检测，它们将被组装。
First of all, the slices are laid on a layer.
首先，硅片被置于一层薄膜之上。
然后，使用一台专业圆形锯机将这些硅片从两个方向锯开。
but here is a film, and then they are all sawn through two directions by a special amazingly arc sawing machine.
So the chips are almost separated.
于是，这些芯片几乎被分开了。
这些硅片被小心的包装好，并发往远东的装配中心，曼谷、香港、马尼拉、高雄。
The slices are very carefully packaged, and sent the assembly center in the far east,  Bangkok, Hongkong, Manyla, or Gaoxiong in Taiwan.
End. Nov.12th,2012, Yang Liu, BIPT
完 2012/11/12，刘洋，北京石油化工学院